Tim CD Lucas

PERSONAL INFORMATION

ĭ timcdlucas@gmail.com email

@timcdlucas @statsforbios twitter

github www.github.com/timcdlucas

Google scholar scholar

phone 07415 863 536

PRESENT APPOINTMENT

2020-present University of Oxford

Senior Post Doc. I am currently working as a senior post doc. with Deirdre Hollingsworth and

> Graham Medley. My position will involve developing methods for quantifying the value of information for surveys of neglected tropical diseases. I will be also be working with colleague on disease specific projects, contributing to software and promoting good research software practices such as version

control and unit testing.

University of Oxford, Malaria Atlas Project 2016-2020

Post Doc. I worked as a postdoctoral research scientist in geospatial epidemiology with the Malaria Atlas Project at the University of Oxford. I have made large

contributions to the first high resolution, global, space-time estimates of both Plasmodium falciparum and P. vivax leading to two high-profile publications. To this end I have developed new statistical methods that combine machine learning and geostatistics. I have also supervised research assistants on smaller projects,

leading to one publication.

PREVIOUS APPOINTMENTS

2018-2019 Shared parental leave

Parental leave Six months shared parental leave.

> Jan-July 2016 CBER, UCL

Research I was the staff programmer for the Centre of Biodiversity and Environment Programmer Research at UCL. I worked on two main projects. I worked with the Madingley

Model to enable this ecological model to run on a *high performance cluster*. Secondly, I translated code from *Mathematica to R* for analyses of measurements

of 3D objects used in *paleontological research*.

EDUCATION

University College London, CoMPLEX 2012-2016

PhD The role of population structure and size in determining bat pathogen richness

> I used network epidemiological models and phylogenetic methods to study the epidemiology of bat-borne diseases with applications to zoonotic surveillance. I conceived the projects and managed my own budget. [pdf]

Supervisors: Prof. Kate Jones & Dr Hilde Herbots

2011-2012 University College London, CoMPLEX

MRes Modelling Biological Complexity · Merit

> Projects included adapting 'ideal gas' models to acoustic data, analysing moment closures for a pair-approximation model of plant ecology and applying a

novel machine learning method to a library of bat calls.

University of Sheffield, Animal & Plant Sciences 2006-2010

MBioSci Zoology · First

> For my final project I used wavelet analysis to study multi-annual cycles in malaria incidence in Thailand.

OTHER RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

Autumn 2014 Zoön: An R package for reproducible SDMs

Internship I wrote the first version of an R package for reproducible species distribution

modelling. [Github]

Smithsonian Tropical Research Institute and 2011

Chiloé Silvestre, Chilé

Volunteer Fieldwork in Panamá and Chilé: Anolis dewlap evolution, gut length plasticity

Fieldwork in Red-eyed tree frogs and two weeks trapping Darwin's foxes.

> August 2010 University of Sheffield

Summer I studied the evolutionary response of plant communities to climate change. I Internship

collected, propagated and analysed plants collected from the field.

University of York, YCCSA August 2009

TRANSIT I studied collective foraging behaviour by programming a complex 3D foraging

Internship model in Java and running large simulations.

OTHER APPOINTMENTS AND AFFILIATIONS

Peer Review Journals Reviewed for:

> Journal of Theoretical Biology, BMC Infectious Diseases, PLoS Pathogens, Malaria Journal, Methods in Ecology and Evolution, Global Ecology and Biogeography, Ecology and Evolution, Remote Sensing in Ecology and Conservation, ROpenSci, National Academy Science Letters.

PEER-REVIEWED PUBLICATIONS

Weiss DJ, Lucas TCD, Nguyen M, et al. (2019) The global landscape of 2019 Plasmodium falciparum prevalence, incidence, and mortality 2000–2017. The Lancet 394, 10195, 322–331. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(19)31097-9 [pdf]

> Battle KE, Lucas TCD, Nguyen M, et al. (2019) Mapping the global endemicity and clinical burden of Plasmodium vivax 2000-2017. The Lancet 394, 10195, 332-343. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(19)31096-7 [pdf]

Zhu SJ, et al. (2019) The origins and relatedness structure of mixed infections vary with local prevalence of P. falciparum malaria. eLife 8 e40845. doi: 10.7554/eLife.40845 [pdf]

Lucas TCD, Python A & Redding DW (2019) Graphical outputs and Spatial Cross-validation for the R-INLA package using INLAutils. The R Journal. In Review

Lucas TCD, Nandi A, et al. (2019) Mapping malaria by sharing spatial information between incidence and prevalence datasets. J. R. Statist. Soc. C. In Review

2018 Weiss DJ, Nelson A, Gibson HS et al. (2018) A global map of travel time to cities to assess inequalities in accessibility in 2015. Nature 553 (7688), 333 [pdf]

Pfeffer D, Lucas TCD, May D et al. (2018) malaria Atlas: an R interface to global malariometric data hosted by the Malaria Atlas Project. Malaria Journal 17:352 doi: 10.1186/s12936-018-2500-5 [pdf]

Redding D, Lucas TCD, Blackburn T & Jones KE. (2017) Evaluating Bayesian 2017 spatial methods for modelling species distributions models with clumped and restricted data. PLoS One [pdf]

> Golding N, August TA, Lucas TCD, Gavaghan DJ, van Loon EE & McInerny G. (2017) The zoon R package for reproducible and shareable species distribution modelling. Methods in Ecology and Evolution. doi: 10.1111/2041-210X.12858 [pdf]

- Lucas TCD*, Moorcroft EA*, Freeman R, Rowcliffe MJ & Jones KE. (2015) A 2015 generalised random encounter model for estimating animal density with remote sensor data. Methods in Ecology and Evolution. doi: 10.1111/2041-210X.12346 [pdf]
- Walters CL, Collen A, Lucas TCD, Mroz K, Sayer CA and Jones KE. (2013) 2013 Challenges of Using Bioacoustics to Globally Monitor Bats. in Bat Evolution, Ecology, and Conservation. Springer New York. 479-499.
 - * Co-first authors.

GLOBAL BURDEN OF DISEASE PUBLICATIONS

2018 GBD 2017 Risk Factor Collaborators (2018) Global, regional, and national comparative risk assessment of 84 behavioural, environmental and occupational, and metabolic risks or clusters of risks for 195 countries and territories, 1990–2017: a systematic analysis for the Global Burden of Disease Study 2017. The Lancet, 392 [pdf]

> GBD 2017 Disease and Injury Incidence and Prevalence Collaborators (2018) Global, regional, and national incidence, prevalence, and years lived with disability for 354 diseases and injuries for 195 countries and territories, 1990–2017: a systematic analysis for the Global Burden of Disease Study 2017. The Lancet, 392 [pdf]

> GBD 2017 DALYs and HALE Collaborators (2018) Global, regional, and national disability-adjusted life-years (DALYs) for 359 diseases and injuries and healthy life expectancy (HALE) for 195 countries and territories, 1990–2017: a systematic analysis for the Global Burden of Disease Study 2017. The Lancet, 392 [pdf]

> GBD 2017 Mortality Collaborators (2018) Global, regional, and national age-sex-specific mortality and life expectancy, 1950–2017: a systematic analysis for the Global Burden of Disease Study 2017. The Lancet, 392 [pdf]

GBD 2016 Healthcare Access and Quality Collaborators (2017) Measuring performance on the Healthcare Access and Quality Index for 195 countries and territories and selected subnational locations: a systematic analysis from the Global Burden of Disease Study 2016. The Lancet, 391 (10136) [pdf]

GBD 2016 Disease and Injury Incidence and Prevalence Collaborators (2017) Global, regional, and national incidence, prevalence, and years lived with disability for 328 diseases and injuries for 195 countries, 1990–2016: a systematic analysis for the Global Burden of Disease Study 2016. The Lancet, 390 [pdf]

GBD 2016 Causes of Death Collaborators (2017) Global, regional, and national age-sex specific mortality for 264 causes of death, 1980–2016: a systematic analysis for the Global Burden of Disease Study 2016. The Lancet, 390 [pdf]

GBD 2016 DALYs and HALE Collaborators (2017) Global, regional, and national disability-adjusted life-years (DALYs) for 333 diseases and injuries and healthy life expectancy (HALE) for 195 countries and territories, 1990–2016: a systematic analysis for the Global Burden of Disease Study 2016. The Lancet, 390[pdf]

GBD 2016 SDG Collaborators (2017) Measuring progress and projecting attainment on the basis of past trends of the health-related Sustainable Development Goals in 188

2017

countries: an analysis from the Global Burden of Disease Study 2016. The Lancet, 390 [pdf]

PEER-REVIEWED CONFERENCE PROCEEDINGS

2019 **Lucas TCD**, Nandi A, Nguyen M, et al. (2019) Model ensembles with different response variables for base and meta models: malaria disaggregation regression combining prevalence and incidence data. ISI World Statistics Congress Proceedings (In press)

Law HC, Sejdinovic D, et al. (2018) Variational learning on aggregate outputs with Gaussian processes. Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems [pdf]

INVITED CONFERENCE TALKS

2017 Predicting malaria risk from diverse and multilevel data.
Plenary at SDCS2017, Springer

SOFTWARE

Pfeffer D, Lucas TCD, May D, Keddie S, Rozier J, Gibson H. *malariaAtlas: An R Interface to Open-Access Malaria Data, Hosted by the 'Malaria Atlas Project'*. www.github.com/malaria-atlas-project/malariaAtlas

Lucas TCD, Python A, Redding D. *INLAutils: Utility Functions for 'INLA'*. www.github.com/timcdlucas/INLAutils

Goswami A, Lucas TCD, Sivasubramaniam P, Finarelli J. A Maximum Likelihood Approach to the Analysis of Modularity. www.github.com/timedlucas/EMMLi

Lucas TCD, Goswami A. paleomorph: Geometric Morphometric Tools for Paleobiology. www.github.com/timcdlucas/paleomorph

August T, **Lucas TCD**, Golding N, van Loon E, McInerny G. *Zoon: Reproducible, Accessible & Shareable Species Distribution Modelling*. www.github.com/zoonproject/zoon

Lucas TCD. palettetown: Use Pokemon Inspired Colour Palettes www.github.com/timcdlucas/palettetown

TEACHING AND SUPERVISION

2019 $\,\cdot\,$ Co-wrote and ran an afternoon workshop. "Advanced Statistical Modelling with TMB".

2019 · Thesis committee for PhD student Dan Pfeffer.

2018 · Supervised two research assistants on side projects resulting in one publication (pdf).

2017 $\,\cdot\,$ Wrote and gave a two day workshop 'Geospatial statistics with R and INLA' at UiTM, Malaysia.

2015 · Demonstrator for reproducible species distribution modelling workshop run by Quantitative Ecology special interest group at BES.

2013–2014 \cdot Online tutor for SysMIC, a course for teaching quantitative skills to biologists.

COMPUTATIONAL SKILLS

Statistical methods

Geospatial statistics, machine learning, Bayesian inference.

Languages

R (eight years), Python, Matlab, Mathematica, Java, SQL.

Other

Experience in R package development, Git/Github, unit testing, continuous integration, shell/ssh and high performance computing.

REFEREES

Prof. Peter Gething Prof. Kate Jones

Professor of Epidemiology Chair of Ecology and Biodiversity

Big Data Institute Centre for Biodiversity and Environment

University of Oxford Research

Oxford University College London

United Kingdom Gower Street
OX3 7LF London

United Kingdom WC1E 6BT

Tel: +44 (0)2476 574710

1st April, 2020